Guide to the Department of Botany, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Department of Botany, Yale University, records
1907-1950
RU 425
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
21.25
The records consist of office files, correspondence, photographs, and memoranda documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Department of Botany, which no longer exists as a separate academic unit.
Yale University. Dept. of Botany
Evans, Alexander W. (Alexander William), 1868-1959
Nichols, George E. (George Elwood), 1882-1939
Sinnott, Edmund W. (Edmund Ware), 1888-1958
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 14-B (YRG 14-B), Records of Academic Departments and Programs of the Yale Faculty of Arts and Sciences
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See inventory for details
Arrangement
The records are arranged in 9 series: I. George E. Nichols Correspondence, 1907-1939. II. Alexander W. Evans Correspondence, 1918-1944. III. Edmund W. Sinnott Correspondence, 1940-1945. IV. McGraw-Hill Book Company Correspondence, 1926-1935. V. Marsh and Farnum Gardens Yale Preserve, 1924-1950. VI. Osborn Botanical Library correspondence, 1915-1933. VII. Herbarium correspondence, 1915-1934. VIII. Departmental papers, 1926-1950. IX. Botanical photographs.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of office files, correspondence, photographs, and memoranda documenting the activities and operations of the Yale Department of Botany, which no longer exists as a separate academic unit
Botany -- Study and teaching; Universities and colleges -- Administration; Universities and colleges -- Departments; Photographs; McGraw-Hill Book Company; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Curricula; Yale University -- Employees; Yale University -- Faculty; Yale University. Dept. of Botany
- George E. Nichols, correspodence, 1907-1939; Series I
  - General
    - A, 1907-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)
    - B, 1905-1929 (Box 1, Folder 7-11)
    - B, 1930-1939 (Box 2, Folder 12-16)
    - C, 1905-1926 (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
    - C, 1927-1939 (Box 3, Folder 21-26)
    - D, 1908-1939 (Box 3, Folder 27-30)
    - E-F, 1906-1927 (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - E-F, 1927-1939 (Box 4, Folder 33-37)
    - G, 1907-1929 (Box 4, Folder 38-40)
    - G, 1930-1938 (Box 5, Folder 41-43)
    - H-I-J, 1907-1931 (Box 5, Folder 44-48)
    - H-I-J, 1932-1939 (Box 6, Folder 49-51)
    - K, 1908-1933, 1929-1938 (Box 6, Folder 52-55)
    - L, 1905-1913, 1916-1929 (Box 6, Folder 56-58)
    - L, 1930-1938 (Box 7, Folder 59-61)
    - M, 1903-1935 (Box 7, Folder 62-68)
    - M, 1936-1939 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - N-O, 1907-1938 (Box 8, Folder 70-73)
    - P-Q, 1907-1938 (Box 8, Folder 74-78)
    - R, 1905-1927 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - R, 1928-1939 (Box 9, Folder 80-82)
    - S, 1905-1932 (Box 9, Folder 83-88)
    - S, 1933-1938 (Box 10, Folder 89-92)
    - T-U-V, 1905-1939 (Box 10, Folder 93-98)
    - W, 1906-1939 (Box 11, Folder 99-104)
    - X-Y-Z, 1910-1936 (Box 11, Folder 105-106)
  - University correspondence
    - A, 1927-1935 (Box 11, Folder 107)
    - B, 1927-1936 (Box 11, Folder 108)
    - C, 1927-1936 (Box 11, Folder 109)
    - D, 1928-1936 (Box 12, Folder 110)
    - E-F, 1928-1936 (Box 12, Folder 111)
    - G, 1929-1936 (Box 12, Folder 112)
    - H-I-J, 1925, 1928-1937 (Box 12, Folder 113)
    - K-L, 1927-1937 (Box 12, Folder 114)
    - M, 1927-1936 (Box 12, Folder 115)
    - N-O, 1928-1936 (Box 12, Folder 116)
    - P-Q, 1930-1936 (Box 12, Folder 117)
    - R, 1929-1936 (Box 12, Folder 118)
    - S, 1929-1937 (Box 12, Folder 119)
    - T-U-V, 1931-1937 (Box 12, Folder 120)
    - W-X-Y-Z, 1927-1937 (Box 12, Folder 121)
  - Ecological classification of plant communities
    - Ecological Classification of Plant Communities (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Correspondence previous to 1921 (Box 12, Folder 122)
    - Ecological Classification of Plant Communities (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Correspondence with Cooper et al. 1921-1922 (Box 12, Folder 123)
    - Ecological Classification of Plant Communities (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Copies of Circular letters sent out in 1921, plus summary of replies to come (Box 13, Folder 124)
    - Ecological Classification of Plant Communities (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Replies to Circular letter No. 1 (1921) (Box 13, Folder 125)
    - Ecological Classification of Plant Communities (Box 13, Folder 126)
    - Replies to Circular letter No. 2 (1921) (Box 13, Folder 126)
- Alexander W. Evans, correspondence, 1918-1944; Series II
  - A, 1918-1942 (Box 14, Folder 1-6)
  - B, 1918-1930 (Box 14, Folder 7-10)
  - B, 1931-1941, 1943-1944 (Box 15, Folder 11-14)
  - C, 1918-1944 (Box 15, Folder 15-20)
  - D, 1918-1935, 1937-1944 (Box 16, Folder 21-25)
  - E-F, 1911, 1913, 1915, 1918-1933, 1937-1939 (Box 16, Folder 26-30)
  - E-F, 1933-1937, 1940-1944 (Box 17, Folder 31-32)
  - G, 1919-1942 (Box 17, Folder 33-38)
  - H-I-J, 1918-1920 (Box 17, Folder 39)
  - H-I-J, 1920-1937 (Box 18, Folder 40-45)
  - H-I-J, 1938-1943 (Box 19, Folder 46)
  - K-L, 1914, 1918-1941 (Box 19, Folder 47-53)
  - K-L, 1942-1944 (Box 20, Folder 54)
  - M, 1913, 1918-1944 (Box 20, Folder 55-60)
  - N-O, 1918-1922 (Box 20, Folder 61-62)
  - N-O, 1921-1943 (Box 21, Folder 63-66)
  - P-Q, 1918-1944 (Box 21, Folder 67-71)
  - R, 1918-1924, 1926-1933 (Box 22, Folder 72-74)
  - Robbins, C.A., 1927-1929 (Box 22, Folder 75-76)
  - R, 1932-1943 (Box 22, Folder 77)
  - S, 1900, 1918-1921 (Box 22, Folder 78-79)
  - S, 1921-1944 (Box 23, Folder 80-87)
  - T-U-V, 1919-1923 (Box 23, Folder 88)
  - T-U-V, 1923-1940 (Box 24, Folder 89-96)
  - T-U-V, 1940-1944 (Box 25, Folder 97)
  - W, 1919-1940 (Box 25, Folder 98-100)
  - X-Y-Z, 1918-1943 (Box 25, Folder 101-102)
- Edmund W. Sinnott, correspondence, 1940-1945; Series III
  - A, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 1)
  - B, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 2-6)
  - C, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 7-8)
  - D, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 9-10)
  - E-F, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 11-13)
  - G, 1940-1945 (Box 26, Folder 14-15)
  - H-I-J, 1940-1945 (Box 27, Folder 16-17)
  - K-L, 1940-1945 (Box 27, Folder 18-19)
  - M, 1940-1945 (Box 27, Folder 20-21)
  - N-O, 1941-1945 (Box 27, Folder 22)
  - P-Q, 1940-1945 (Box 27, Folder 23-24)
  - R, 1940-1945 (Box 27, Folder 25-26)
  - S, 1942-1943, 1940-1941, 1944-1945 (Box 27, Folder 27-29)
  - T-U-V, 1940-1942 (Box 27, Folder 30)
  - T-U-V, 1943-1945 (Box 28, Folder 31)
  - W, 1940-1945 (Box 28, Folder 32-34)
  - X-Y-Z, 1941-1945 (Box 28, Folder 35)
- McGraw-Hill book company correspondence, 1926-1935; Series IV
  - A-D, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 1)
  - E-G, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 2)
  - H-I-J, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 3)
  - K-R, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 4)
  - S-T, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 5)
  - W-Z, 1926-1928 (Box 29, Folder 6)
  - A-G, 1928-1931 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - H-S, 1928-1931 (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - T-Z, 1928-1931 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - A-S, 1931-1935 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - T-W, 1931-1935 (Box 30, Folder 11)
- Marsh and Farnum Gardens Yale Preserve, 1924-1950; Series V
  - Correspondence, annual reports, lists, employments, financial papers
    - A-W, 1927-1929, 1932 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - B-F, 1926-1929 (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - G-L, 1926-1929 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - M-S, 1926-1929 (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - T-W, 1926-1929 (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Yale Preserve: annual reports, 1926-1946 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Marsh Gardens: annual reports, 1928-1949 (Box 31, Folder 7)
    - Garden, (1929) (Box 31, Folder 8)
    - Marsh Garden: plant material 1. General 2. Iris List, 1924-1940 (Box 31, Folder 9)
    - Marsh Garden: wild flower garden lists, 1926-1940 (Box 31, Folder 10)
    - Garden, 1927 (Box 32, Folder 11)
    - Preserve: construction, 1940-1950 (Box 32, Folder 12)
    - Yale Preserve: employment (Box 32, Folder 13)
    - Marsh Garden: employment (Box 32, Folder 14)
    - Marsh Garden: upkeep 1. General 2. Hillhouse G.H. (Box 32, Folder 15)
    - Yale Preserve: equipment (Box 32, Folder 16)
    - Marsh Garden: financial statement, 1939-1944 (Box 32, Folder 17)
    - Financial papers, 1927-1950 (Box 32, Folder 18)
    - Yale Preserve, Finance, maintenance, maps, photos, meetings, planting lists and general correspondence, 1940-1950 (Box 32, Folder 19)
- Osborn Botanical Library correspondence, 1915-1933; Series VI
  - Correspondence A-Z, 1926-1931 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence General, 1915-1933 (Box 33, Folder 2)
- Herbarium correspondence, 1915-1934; Series VII
  - Correspondence General, 1915-1934 (Box 34, Folder 1)
  - A-G, 1915-1934 (Box 34, Folder 2)
  - H-Z, 1915-1934 (Box 34, Folder 3)
- Departmental papers, 1926-1950; Series VIII
  - Correspondence - general, 1927-1936
    - Correspondence, 1927-1928
      - A-F (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - G (Box 35, Folder 2)
      - H-S (Box 35, Folder 3)
      - T-Z (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - General
    - Correspondence, 1928-1932
      - A-E (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - F-L (Box 36, Folder 6)
      - M-R (Box 36, Folder 7)
      - S-Z (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence A-T, 1933-1936 (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Recommendations A-Z (Box 36, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence with section officers, officers of associated societies, representatives on AAAS Council (Box 36, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence with section officers, officers of associated societies, representatives on AAAS Council (Box 37, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence: officers of the society and of affiliated societies (Box 37, Folder 13)
  - American Journal of Botany, correspondence, 1928-1933
    - A-C, 1928-1930 (Box 37, Folder 14)
    - D-F, 1928-1930 (Box 37, Folder 15)
    - G-M, 1928-1930 (Box 37, Folder 16)
    - O-S, 1928-1930 (Box 37, Folder 17)
    - T-Z, 1928-1930 (Box 37, Folder 18)
    - A-D, 1931-1933 (Box 37, Folder 19)
    - E-L, 1931-1933 (Box 38, Folder 20)
    - M-Z, 1931-1933 (Box 38, Folder 21)
  - Botanical Society of America, correspondence and applications, 1931-1935
    - Correspondence: applications for membership, 1931-1933, 1935 (Box 38, Folder 22-25)
    - Correspondence Miscellaneous (Box 38, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence miscellaneous, 1933-1946
    - General, 1939-1940 (Box 39, Folder 27)
    - A-L, 1939-1940 (Box 39, Folder 28)
    - M-Z, 1939-1940 (Box 39, Folder 29)
    - Graduate School, 1940-1945 (Box 39, Folder 30-31)
    - Division of Biological Sciences, 1940-1945 (Box 39, Folder 32)
    - Exams, 1940-1945 (Box 39, Folder 33)
    - General: exams, 1933-1946 (Box 39, Folder 34)
    - School of Agricultural Science, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 35)
    - A-G, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 36)
    - H-N, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 37)
    - O-V, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 38)
    - W-Z, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 39)
    - Finance, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 40)
    - Applications of members elected in 1936, including Atlantic City, 1933-1946 (Box 40, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - Comprehensive exams, 1930-1948 (Box 46, Folder 72-74)
    - Comprehensive exams: Sheffield Scientific (Box 46, Folder 75)
    - Former personnel
      - A-D, 1935-1946 (Box 47, Folder 76)
      - E-L, 1935-1949 (Box 47, Folder 77)
      - M-O, 1935-1949 (Box 47, Folder 78)
      - P-T, 1935-1949 (Box 47, Folder 79)
      - W-Z, 1935-1949 (Box 47, Folder 80)
    - Osborn Botanical Lab: financial papers (Box 48, Folder 81)
    - Statement of budget, allowance and expenditure (Box 48, Folder 82)
    - Genetics Society of America (Box 48, Folder 83)
    - Genetics Congress: correspondence (Box 48, Folder 84)
    - Bisby (Box 48, Folder 85)
    - Miscellaneous bills
      - Botanical Garden (Box 48, Folder 86)
      - Class lists and records (Box 48, Folder 87)
      - Departmental budgets and finances (Box 48, Folder 88)
    - Miss Richter's work (Box 48, Folder 89)
    - Miss Benedix's work (Box 48, Folder 90)
    - Thesis by L.G. Schermerhorn (Box 48, Folder 91)
    - Work by F.A. Varrelman (Box 48, Folder 92)
    - Work by G.H. Smith (Box 48, Folder 93)
    - Work by L.S. Jaffe (Box 48, Folder 94)
    - "Evidence for Shape Genes" (Box 48, Folder 95)
- Botanical photographs, Series IX
  - International Physical Geography Excursion (Box 49–50)
  - Dendrology: Terminal Winter Buds (Box 51–54)
  - Connecticut (Box 55–57)
  - Cape Breton, Adirondacks, Cape Cod, Alaska, Maine (Box 58–60)